This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine, online at
computer.org/software.
>> [music]
>> Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host, Gregory Kaphhammer.
Today's guest is Dave Airlie. Dave is a
long-time Linux kernel maintainer and a
distinguished engineer at Red Hat. Dave,
welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
>> Hi Greg, thanks for having me on.
>> I'm delighted to talk to you today about
Linux kernel maintenance. Dave, you're
the direct rendering manager subsystem
maintainer in the Linux kernel and you
have nearly two decades of kernel
maintenance experience and I'm super
happy to learn from you throughout the
episode. Are you ready to dive in?
>> Yes, let's go.
>> Okay. So, at the very start, I mentioned
a moment ago that you're the maintainer
of something that's called DRM. Can you
just tell us quickly what is DRM so we
know the kind of work you do on the
Linux kernel?
>> Well, since DRM is a bit of an
overloaded term, it's not the bad one. I
suppose is the best way to describe it.
It's a thing called the direct rendering
manager, which is a legacy name for what
was really just the GPU or graphics
support subsystem in the Linux kernel.
The name was given to a small component,
maybe 20 years ago and we have expanded
on it, but we just kept the name. So, I
think the name is DRM. I don't think
direct rendering manager even really
makes sense for what it does anymore.
So, stick with the acronym, but it
pretty much when you hear DRM, just
think GPU graphics accelerators.
>> Okay. So, we're going to use DRM and
your experience with maintaining it
throughout the episode, but to get us
started, we want to talk a little bit
about some of the scale and structure
issues associated with the Linux kernel
and we're going to talk about subsystem
workflows and how you do release
engineering and we'll use DRM as
concrete examples throughout the
episode. So with that in mind, can you
tell us a little bit about the scope and
the architecture of the Linux kernel?
How many maintainers are there? How many
subsystems are there? Please give us a
few initial insights.
>> Yeah, the Linux kernel is well, we
consider it's probably the biggest
software engineering project in the
world. That's what we like to say. In
terms of maintainers, the number is very
changeable, I would say on average it's
between 80 and 100 and 150. The varying
levels of what a maintainer is and where
they sit in the hierarchy moves a lot.
We have every year maintainer summit
where Linus invites like the top 30
maintainers to that. So that's kind of a
number of like the top level people that
Linus needs to talk to, but that scales
out there into a hierarchy that can
expand to up to 100, I would say, in the
kernel at the moment. In terms of
subsystems, again, there's no strict
definition of what exactly a subsystem
is. A subsystem is something that a
maintainer maintains usually. So in the
same sense of there is the number of
subsystems that there are the number of
maintainers and some maybe not one is to
one, but it's pretty close. But there
are a number of major subsystems would
probably be like the graphics subsystem,
the networking subsystem, the CPU like
x86 support, arm64 support and those are
the major areas, storage, file systems,
memory management. So they're probably
the biggest groupings that we have.
>> Okay, so we've got DRM as one subsystem
and CPU scheduling or memory management
or file systems. Those are all examples
of subsystems. So if we take DRM as an
example, how many people are actually
working with you as the maintainer of
the DRM subsystem?
>> If you'd asked me this yesterday, I
would have said 100, but I actually ran
the numbers last night and apparently we
have over 300 people contributing every
kernel release to the DRM subsystem,
which actually surprised me just as
much. So they don't all work directly
with me again. We have a hierarchical
system. I probably work on a weekly to
fortnightly basis with maybe 20 people
in that range, 15 to 20. And then that
they work in the hierarchy with the
other grouping. But yes, I was surprised
that we have up to 300 contributors per
kernel for the DRM subsystem.
>> Okay, so there's 300 people and they're
somehow reporting to you and you're
managing their work and you're reviewing
their pull requests. Can you give us at
a high-level a rough idea, what are
those 300 people doing and then what are
you doing when it comes to managing the
infrastructure for DRM in the Linux
kernel?
>> So this is probably an area where the
DRM subsystem is a little bit different
to a lot of the other subsystems in that
I actually have quite a large hierarchy.
I would think more like a corporate
style of There is two co-maintainers,
myself and Simon Vetter. And then below
us we have a range of maybe six or seven
more feeding into us and then they have
a range of people feeding into them and
then there's all of the front-line
developers probably feeding into that.
So the hierarchy is, depending where you
sit on it, just like in a corporate
structure, is very different for what
your job is. So my role, a lot of it is
I suppose I would call facilitating and
creating an environment for people to be
able to work in and be happy to work in.
My main weekly task is I deal with
Linus. I submit the pull request to
Linus on a weekly basis. I gather all
the pull requests from the people below
me and I send them up to Linus. The
amount of review I personally do on
those pull requests is very limited at
this point because they are so large
already that I have to trust that the
maintainers below me have done
appropriate review and they have to
trust that the maintainers below them
have done appropriate review. The review
all happens in public on the mailing
list so we can always go back and
reference it, but for me personally on a
daily weekly basis, I don't often review
the pull requests that that much. I do a
set of standard builds on them. I make
sure there's no
they don't build. That's a big problem.
But mostly it's a maintenance role for
me is very different than a standard
maintainer. A lot of the standard
maintainers will be applying the patches
to our trees, checking the quality of
the work, and making sure that it's
suitable for going upstream to me.
>> Thanks, that's really helpful. So, I
have the understanding that people are
in a way working for or reporting to
you, and you mentioned a moment ago that
you're reporting to Linus Torvalds as
well. Can you tell us a little bit more
about how you report to Linus and what
type of work you do on behalf of this
core leader for the Linux kernel?
>> Yeah, so one thing with the kernel is
Linus is very delicate. He delegates a
lot of trust to the top-level
maintainers, and it is kind of like I
hate the word fiefdom, but you own your
garden. Like you're in charge of
maintaining that section of the kernel,
and he trusts you until you give him a
reason not to, I suppose. I've worked
with him now for 20 years. I've had a
few public falling out with him. They're
easy to find on the internet. But
overall, we don't have a huge amount of
interaction. Most of my interactions
with Linus are at the maintainer summit
once a year. We'll meet up and we'll
have it We'll just talk about life, but
mostly it's about normal things. We both
like scuba diving, so there's a cool you
know, things like that. But in terms of
the kernel, every week I send him an
official pull request with the list of
all of the fixes for that week from all
of the people in my group. And he then
will process that. If he processes that,
the system will send an automatic reply
telling me that Linus has taken the
request. If you get a reply from Linus
himself, that's usually only if you've
done something wrong. He is not really
good at giving positive feedback. He is
much better at giving something wrong
feedback. He's known for not giving the
positive side. So, you generally look
for the Linus on the reply and hope it
you don't see it, and then things go
along swimmingly. Once every Like we'll
go into the release cycle later, but
once every 9 or 10 weeks you have to
send the big pull request, which is all
of the work that is due for the next
kernel. That's the one that often upsets
him because that's the one where you
will have a lot of change, and there is
always regression with change, and you
just have to hope that he doesn't catch
a really bad regression, or you haven't
messed up some other part of the kernel.
But, in general, my interactions with
Linus are purely on the I send him a
weekly email. I hope he doesn't have a
problem with it. If he has a problem
with it, I delegate that down to the
people who caused the problem, and I
generally accept the I'm an umbrella, I
suppose, as well. You know, need to
protect the people under me from his
wrath, and he's calmed down over the
years, but I'm used to it at this stage,
so it's I sometimes have to take an hour
or two to breathe, and then I'm good.
>> Okay, so that's really giving us a nice
sense in the day of the life of a Linux
kernel maintainer, and we're going to do
a deep dive into all those topics in a
moment. But, before we do that, can you
tell us a little bit about some of the
specific challenges that you face when
it comes to maintaining DRM in the Linux
kernel?
>> I think the biggest challenge I've faced
over the years, and Simon, and my
co-maintainer, has been great at helping
with this, is that the scale of things
when you get to being this big is quite
hard to both communicate to other
maintainers, and to have interesting
topics with other co-maintainers who are
dealing at the 10 people level, or the
40 people level. They don't quite
understand why the scale of changes when
you get to our level. Like, even when I
was taking with 100 people going through
it, the scale problem is different. But,
now that I'm taking 300, I'm like,
"Okay, now our scale problems are
definitely valid and different than
theirs." So, for example, we have to
have a hierarchy. We have a common tree
where everyone has commit access for a
bunch of things, and we try to have a
group maintainership model, which isn't
something as standard in the kernel. X86
subsystem kind of did it with three
people. We've done it now with maybe 30
to 40 people. I think in our group
maintainers, there's probably more.
There's three maintainers, but there's a
group of committers. So, that system is
different than everyone else's. That's
probably one of the biggest challenges.
Like, scaling the standard kernel
development processes up to our size of
the subsystem has been the biggest
challenge we faced over the last years.
And in my world, a lot of my job has
been to just sort of step away and not
let my, I suppose, ego or my own niched
workflows drive everything else's. And I
need to accept that, "Okay, this is
something that makes the community
better, and maybe it makes my life a bit
harder, but I need to use these scripts
or just develop methods technology
because it makes it easier for everyone
else. And often we have a problem where
over the years we got our little niche
of how we develop things and we stay in
it. And being able to not do that has
been very good for me and in the helping
the subsystem to grow, I think, because
scale is hard.
>> So, you've talked about scale from the
perspective of the number of humans, and
you mentioned there are like 300 people
who are developing various types of
patches or change sets. Can you tell our
listeners a little bit about the size
and the scope and the scale of your part
of the Linux kernel when it comes to
things like lines of code or size of a
change set? Other details that you can
share there?
>> Yeah, the lines of code is a bit of an
outlier for us because we have a huge
amount of auto-generated headers, which
both piss people off and are very
valuable for us for a few drivers. But,
I think we're talking in the at least a
million lines of code under my purview
in that subsystem. The headers are
probably add another million or half a
million onto that. But, so yeah, you're
probably talking at least in the 1
million to 2 million lines of code. I
don't have accurate numbers on the
number of change sets I process, but I
would say it's in the 2,000 to 3,000
every kernel cycle. So, every 3 months
I'd say we put in about 2 to 3,000. Of
that, I would say I probably process
maybe 50 to 60 pull requests from
sub-maintainers in that cycle as well.
On average on a week, I'd say I process
maybe five to six pull requests from
sub-maintainers, and they normally at
this stage of the fixes stages of the
kernel, probably only have 10 to 15
patches in them. But everything in the
big part of the merge request, that's
where all the majority of things come
through.
>> That makes a lot of sense. Now, I know
many people who use Linux, they have
heard of this idea of an RC build or a
release candidate build. And so in this
next phase of our show, I'm hoping that
we can give the listeners a sense of
your workflow or the cadence or the
processes that you follow in Linux
kernel maintenance. So, can you tell us
a little bit about how many weeks you
work for until you get to a release
candidate? Can you give us a few details
about that process as we dive in?
>> Yeah, I'll probably give the general
overview of how the kernel works and
probably a bit more into what we do. So,
overall in the kernel has what we call a
9-to-10 week release cycle, depending on
how happy Linus is. It can go 9 weeks,
it can go 10 weeks if he feels there's
been a reason. Mostly, we've been doing
9 weeks lately. We had one 10 week last
time. The way that works is the first 2
weeks of every new kernel development
cycle are called the merge window.
That's where Linus takes all of the pull
requests from all of the authors, all of
the maintainers under him, and he puts
them all together and stabilizes that
for 2 weeks. And we're hoping in that 2
weeks that that's a runnable kernel. At
the end of that 2 weeks, he'll release
what's called RC1. And then on a weekly
basis, usually on a Sunday afternoon
Pacific time, he will release RC2, RC3
up until RC7 usually. And then from RC7,
he'll release the final one the
following week. Occasionally, it'll be
an RC8.
Maybe there's been an RC9 once. But it
goes through that cop that cycle. Every
week after the merge window is just
fixes. And everything should be stable.
There should be no new regressions.
Everything There should be no new code.
Linus comes down very heavily if you try
to sneak things in during those weeks.
He's he's very specific that the merge
window is where you drop new stuff and
all after that should just be fixes for
It technically should just be fixes for
regressions. But we often add like to
fixes for general things that we need to
back port or we need to stabilize. But,
in saying that, a lot of people have a
misconception about the merge window.
The merge window is for Linus to merge
the trees that other people have
prepared prior to the merge window. The
merge window is not when you should be
preparing your tree for Linus. The merge
window is not when you should be doing
development that needs to go to Linus.
All that stuff should generally have
been ready for Linus prior to the merge
window and it will have been in a tree
we call Linux next where somebody will
gather all those disparate trees across
the internet and just does merges every
day. That's their job just to sit there
merging every day and find all the
conflicting problems and make sure we
understand that building the tree is
hard and that merging all these
conflicts will happen and that we know
about them in advance. So, when Linus
gets to do all that final merges into
his tree, he has a history of all of the
conflicts and he has knows what's going
to cause problems. He will accept things
that haven't been in Linux next, but he
will be often very unhappy about that or
he will sometimes just say no. It's
generally preferred that we have stuff
ready in advance. Again, that's very
subsystem dependent on how that happens.
I'll go into how we do it in the
graphics subsystem. We have a hierarchy
of trees that come from vendors. So, we
like have an AMD GPU tree, a tree from
Intel, we have tree for Qualcomm. And
then we also have a misc tree for all of
the smaller drivers will cohabitate and
they will all push their changes to
that. We have a hierarchy called a next
tree that we have open all the time. And
when that happen, Linus releases RC6, we
will generally shut our next tree down.
If your stuff isn't in our next tree by
RC6, which gives us usually a two-week
window for us to stabilize, we will
leave it for the next kernel cycle. You
can push it into the next tree, but it
won't get merged till the next kernel
cycle. And that's how we've done that
over the years. We initially were a lot
worse at that, but we've stabilized in
the last four or five years onto that
system and it seems to be working quite
well for us. Pushing in stuff after RC6
is at my discretion usually.
Uh and occasionally I will do it if it's
something I'm personally interested in
or it's sort of a piece of hardware that
we need to get working, but we try to
maintain that because we found for
stability that allowing a free-for-all
after RC6 it hasn't led to quality
results, put it that way. So yes, so
generally that's how we work is that we
set everything up in advance by RC6,
Linus opens his tree two weeks later, I
will send the big huge pull request of
everything that was there at the
previous RC6 to Linus, he will accept
that, he will pull everyone else's in.
When he hits RC1, we will pull that into
our tree and then start generating the
fixes trees based on that and then start
the next bring all the work that
happened between RC6 and that point into
a next tree and go again for the next
window.
>> Okay, so that's really helpful and
you're giving us some insights into
release candidates and how they're
actually built and the cycle that you go
through. Just to make sure all of our
listeners are on the same page, you
mentioned the words regression and then
also the word tree. Can you concretely
define a regression and the tree and
give us some other insights into how
those work in kernel maintenance?
>> I'll start with tree because it's
probably easier. Now is a git tree is
what we call the kernel tree is really
just the kernel checkout, but now with
git it's the git tree, the git checkout,
the git repos. So we have like a number
of git repositories that we use that are
we then have some for DRM, we've got a
multiple of them for DRM and then
there's what we build a hierarchy from.
So when I say tree that's it, it's just
those git flows of tops into Linus to
me. And for regression, well, I'd love
to define it properly, but yeah, a
regression is made to be something that
broke in RC1. If something is merged
during RC1 that causes anything to go be
worse than it was before RC1, then it's
considered a regression. The standard
method of dealing with regressions is to
revert first, ask questions later, so we
should remove the patch that caused the
problem and then work out what the
problem was and fix it in the next
cycle. That doesn't always happen,
engineers are not brilliant at dealing
with regressions in that way. Often
their instinct is to try and fix it
first, and that often causes a lot of
discussion on what is a regression. Is
this considered a regression? If it's a
regression two kernels ago, is it
something that should be fixed urgently
now? And sometimes it should be more
urgent. So, there's a lot of scope for
what actually regression is, but Linus's
technical definition has always been
something that broke in RC1 and made
life worse for a user.
>> Okay, that's really helpful. So, is a
regression something that's connected to
performance or correctness? I'm guessing
that it could be both of those. Is that
right?
>> Yes, indeed. Anything, to be honest. His
definition is if it made something worse
for a user. Whether that user is having
a performance difference, or that user
is seeing a functional break in their
hardware. But, his thing is if nobody
notices, it's the old if the old tree
falls in the wood. If a regression
happens and nobody notices, it's not
considered a regression till someone
notices. We don't urgently find them,
but yeah, we generally have to be a user
driving them.
>> Cool.
>> So, in the context of the graphics
subsystem and accelerators, can you give
us a few concrete examples of what a
regression would look like?
>> Quite often, a regression actually looks
like your laptop screen not turning on
for us. That's the easiest one to give
is like, my laptop screen is now
flickering or not doing what it used to
do when I had the last kernel and I got
the new kernel. Often it's some of the
rendering on the screen might have an
issue. There maybe my hot plug stopped
working. My suspend and resume stopped
working. Like in the old days, the more
common ones were like, yeah, suspend
resume stopped working, or your laptop
just doesn't light up anymore, which are
fairly obvious regressions. In other
cases, more like on in the data center
and accelerators phase, it's like, yeah,
our workload has gotten slower. Like, I
have this standard workload I test for.
I've upgraded to a new kernel, and
suddenly it's not working as well. Or,
say you have some device like a Steam
Deck and you're trying to move from an
older kernel to a newer kernel, and all
of a sudden the newer kernel device
isn't cooling as well, or it's not
scheduling as well. You're not seeing
the same frame numbers you were. Those
are all considered regressions, and if
you are when reported the generally will
be tried to be hunted down and fixed.
>> And normally those regressions are
reported to you and your team by users,
that is people who are actually using
the Linux kernel on your devices. Is
that the right way to think about it?
>> Yeah, often there will be engineers who
are like embedded in those situations.
So, like for example, if the Steam Deck
has a regression, it will come from a
Valve engineer through AMD, and it will
be reported by that method. It won't
necessarily come to us, but often you
will just get an email on the list from
someone randomly testing an RC on their
laptop and saying, "Hey, this RC doesn't
work." Another layer is distributions
will often take the RC kernels and
package them, and people will be running
the bleeding edge distribution, and then
they will see it. And the distribution
will say, "Oh, this kernel seems to have
broken a bunch of workloads or a bunch
of laptops." And sometimes it'll just be
me sitting here booting it on my laptop
going, "Hey, my laptop's not working."
Those are rare. And And Linus is often
uh Linus will have a specific graphics
card from 10 years ago, and that
graphics card broke, and Linus is the
first person to find it because he just
happens to be the one person that's in
that line that has that card. So, it's
yeah, they come from a lot of places.
>> Looking for a way to stand out in a
competitive job market?
Whether you're trying to land your first
contributor role or prove you can
deliver, take the next step in your
career with the new software
professional certification from the IEEE
Computer Society.
Sign up today at
computer.org/certification.
>> So, in a minute we're going to talk
about many of the tools you use and a
few more of the development and
maintenance processes that you follow.
But before we go into that phase of our
conversation, I wanted to read a quote
from your blog that I thought was really
thought-provoking. So, you wrote, "A
warning then to anyone wishing for more
vendor code sharing between operating
systems. It generally doesn't end with
Linux being better off. That's really
thought-provoking. Can you share a
little bit more about what you meant by
that, Dave?
>> The thing about what people often don't
understand is the incentives for
companies to do things cause results
that are probably not what you expected.
So, you pushing a company to say we want
Linux support for this device, in your
mind, produces a Linux driver for this
device that is well-written, upstream,
maintained piece of code that merges
well with the kernel. But, when you pass
that into a company that is writing
Windows drivers, their first instinct is
how can we share the code between our
Windows driver and our Linux driver to
cut the cost of doing this. In their
mind, that's cutting the cost. In the
real world, it probably doesn't, but
companies work like companies do. So,
often what will happen is they will try
to put a hardware abstraction layer in.
They will try and port their Windows
driver to Linux. They won't start a
rewrite. So, the results you will get
will either be a very second-class
driver or a driver that can't go
upstream or a driver that needs an
impedance layer between the actual
vendor and the upstream. So, you don't
always get the results you envision when
you say I want more Linux code or I want
to use more Windows alignment. So, it's
often good to make sure you don't just
let the company run free with that idea
because the results you'll get 6 months
or a year later won't be what you
wanted.
>> So, it sounds like what you're saying is
that in some way the Linux kernel itself
might become more fragmented or even
harder to support when you start
bringing in this vendored code. Is that
the right way to think about it?
>> Yeah, and it just becomes harder for us
to extract commonality from the code. In
the kernel, one of the big advantages of
the Linux kernel is always is that
because everything is in the same tree,
we do extract commonality quite often.
The commonality we extract is from our
group of drivers, but when you're
working in a world where you've got your
commonalities between your Windows and
your Linux drivers, you have a different
vector for extracting that commonality.
You want to abstract the Linux stuff
away and keep the common stuff between
your Linux and Windows code. But when
the kernel, we want to extract the
common stuff out of all the drivers to
be in Linux and not in the drivers. And
there's a mismatch between your Linux
and Windows, that often gets very
difficult for companies to resolve. So,
yeah, we tend to try to say we want a
Linux driver because we want to be able
to have it optimal in Linux. And if we
see commonalities, we can extract them.
I think the best example I could give
you was wireless. Years ago, there was a
big thing with 802.11 layer, and every
driver was bringing their own 802.11
layers to the party. And someone said,
"Well, why isn't the operating system
providing an 802.11 layer?" And they
did, but still for years we got wireless
drivers which were written with the old
802.11 in mind. So, those things we see
different vectors for commonality than
Windows Linux vendors do.
>> Okay, thanks. That was a really good
example. Now, again, in a moment we're
going to talk about patching and
backporting and things of that nature.
But you also have just hinted at some of
the counterintuitive aspects of
maintaining the Linux kernel. And I know
that many of our listeners may know
mostly about open source software
through GitHub or GitLab or other
systems of that nature. Before we go
into the next phase of our show, can you
say anything about how Linux kernel
maintenance might not work well with the
existing model that you would have on
GitHub?
>> I think it just comes down to what I
said earlier, scale. I think the kernel
process is just so vast and has so many
people that scaling it up through a
single tree would be close to
impossible. So, uh the Git Forge model
of like there's a single central tree
that you send pull requests to just
doesn't scale well for us. And that's I
think what it comes down to. There is
also another side to it. We have a
strong resistance against using
proprietary tooling at all in the in the
Linux development process. That isn't a
top-down Linus-driven thing. Linus is
very flexible on this, but a lot of the
maintainers have personal
strong feelings on these things. So, we
tend to shy away from using anything
proprietary in the development process.
So, GitHub for example, although it uses
Git, is still quite a proprietary
system. In the DRM subsystem, we started
use GitLab more extensively. We use
GitLab for hosting a lot of our trees
and stuff like that. So, yeah, I think
the scale is generally the biggest
problem and the tooling like we're
seeing problems with our tooling as
well. Email and stuff doesn't work like
it did 20 years ago. Gmail holds all of
Gmail doesn't want to talk to you, your
email server is no use. So, there's a
lot of problems we have to solve
ourselves that just because the Git
forges don't solve them, doesn't mean we
don't have to solve them. And we're
working on that with a bunch of tooling
at the moment. So, it's a different
aspect to it.
>> Okay, that makes sense. Now, before you
mentioned the idea of a release
candidate and we talked about RC1
through RC6. I have the understanding
that there's also something called a
stable kernel. What's a stable kernel
and how does that connect to an RC?
>> So, the stable kernel was something Greg
Kroah-Hartman decided to work on. I
can't remember, maybe it's 10 years ago.
He'll he'll correct me if I'm wrong
someday. But, the idea was that Linux's
releases are all very well and good, but
people want to stay on an older release
for longer and still get security fixes
and regression fixes and possibly
hardware fixes and improvements. Maybe
not major functionality improvements,
but quite often they want like a good
baseline so they can build things on. It
all this comes from Android world and
devices where you don't want to be
upgrading the kernel for fear of being
sideswiped by a regression in some other
area. So, you just want to keep going on
the same kernel, but build out on it.
So, the idea of the stable kernel was
shipped. No one said it would be a great
idea, but Greg pushed through and
shipped it. It has it comes out I don't
know what Greg's release schedules are.
I think he does one every week or two as
well and there's a maintenance of about
maybe four or five different stable
kernels over the range of the last maybe
10 or 20. Every so often Greg picks a
kernel as the LTS, which is the
long-term stable release and that kernel
will get maintained by Greg or someone
else. Often some someone else gets
handed that job. One of the The
things of the stable kernel that was
kind of announced was that maintainers
should not be required to add to their
process to enable the stable kernel,
that the stable kernel should try to not
force maintainers to support it, so that
we have an option. I can't say that was
good or bad in the graphics subsystem.
We are both good and bad at helping the
stable kernel. Some parts of us are
really good and some parts are not. We
don't have a great system. We don't do
bespoke work for stable in our group
generally. We let the stable maintainers
take care of it as much as possible, and
occasionally if we see a patch that we
know should go into stable, we will tag
it for that, and people in the hierarchy
know to tag certain things for stable if
it's a regression from two kernels ago.
And often we will automatically add
fixes lines and tag stable on things we
think, and then let them decide whether
there's something that should go into it
or not. But the rules around stable
patches are pretty strict, but they're
not that flexible. They usually should
be less than 100 lines, and it should be
quite self-contained, so we don't like
to get series into the stable kernel.
>> So you just mentioned the next word that
I wanted to talk a little bit more. You
talked about the word patches. Can you
say precisely what is a patch and how do
you manage a patch when you're doing
Linux kernel maintenance?
>> Yeah, that's a good question. Years ago
I don't think I told what I had to
answer, but in the merge request world,
it's a different way of working as in
the kernel we treat a patch as the
smallest unit of work to make a change,
but be very self-contained. We put a lot
of effort into our patch summary Yeah,
got it. Text in the patch because the
commit message is actually very
important from the kernel. A lot of
other merge request flow people put a
lot of work into their merge requests.
We put that work as much as possible
into the commit messages for each patch.
Each patch should be very
self-contained. It should do a single
thing. We It should not be If your
commit message starts having and and
but, then you're like, "Okay, maybe this
should be two patches." So you get the
instincts for what a patch should be
over years of writing patches. You
should not drop a whole new driver in
one patch. You should try and drop
infrastructure changes needed for your
driver, then the core of the driver,
then add features to the driver, and
they should all be well explained. I
suppose the other way to think of a
patch is it's the unit for review. This
is something that should be digestible
by a reviewer, and they should be able
to make a decision on a patch-by-patch
basis whether there's something that we
should accept into the kernel or
something we shouldn't accept in the
kernel or are there some problems when
we need to iterate on again. And then a
patch series is a gathering of those
patches with a cover letter that
describes the overall idea of where
you're going to go with the series, and
then each patch then will take you on
the journey to the result that you want.
>> Okay, that makes sense. Can you tell us
are there some tools that you
specifically use when it comes to
managing a patch or a series of patches?
And then how do you use those tools?
>> Like everything, there's a lot of tools,
and they're all different ones, and
every kernel maintainer probably has
their own set. I think the current core
is Git. Everyone nearly has agreed, like
years ago we had other systems, but Git
is the current core. You generally will
develop all of your changes in a Git
tree on your local machine. You will
When you're finished out with the
development, you'll have to go back and
probably make a patch series out of that
development that is linear and sane,
because often development is not linear
and sane, so you have to go back and
distill your patch series into something
linear and sane, then go through the
process of making sure it's submittable,
making sure you're following the rules,
that it actually is patch series you
want to send out. And then you go
through the process of sending it to the
mailing list. That's where we use that
through email. We have a new tool called
B4. We have a set tool for sending patch
series out. There are also other patch
management systems, so Git isn't always
the best thing to manage patches with,
so there's a number of things series of
tools called Quilt, there's a thing
called StGit. So, depending on how you
want to manage your patches, there are
other alternate tools. I personally,
when I'm writing patch series, and I
don't write a lot of patch series for
the kernel these days, will use just Git
trees, and I will keep the cover letter
just to a side, but that's only because
I'm probably only ever working on one
major patch series at a time anymore.
I'm not doing a lot of streams of work
at that level.
>> Okay, so you have patches and you have
patch series and I'm glad you defined
each of those terms. I also quickly
wanted to talk about the concept of a
backport. What is a backport and how
does it connect to the topics we've
discussed so far?
>> So a backport is probably a many aspects
of what constitutes a backport. So you
can consider a patch going into stable
being a backport as in at the simplest
term a backport is something that you
have to maybe adapt to an older kernel
as opposed to just apply to an older
kernel. So if you have a patch that goes
into like the latest kernel and you want
to apply it to a kernel that's five
kernels old, sometimes that patch will
just apply and it's fine and that's a
technically a backport but it's not
really I've not done anything. But if
you actually have to modify that patch
to make it adapted to the older kernel
API or just the older state of the
driver back then, that's more getting to
what an actual backport is because say
you have a security fix or something in
the new kernel and it's the same
security problem exists in the older
kernel but it's in a very different
state. Like the code that causes has
been changed substantially but there's
still underlying security problems
there. Well then you need to adapt that
fix for that kernel and sometimes it's a
full rewrite. Sometimes it's just a
concept you're applying back but you
still need to do it. You then have to
scale that up again if you're looking
into and I'll talk about about Red Hat
works. So Red Hat has a rail kernel. We
backport subsystems. So like we will
take the full DRM subsystem which is
like thousands of lines of code and
patches and backport that whole on mass
to a kernel that was maybe eight kernels
old. That's like that's extreme
backporting and you see Ubuntu do the
same. You'll see a lot of stable kernels
for devices, Android do a bunch of it.
So backporting is kind of like I won't
say the dirty secret but if you're
actually releasing a product of
something using the Linux kernel, you
would generally be in the market for
having to backport things to that kernel
and need your engineers to do that.
>> How does backporting connect to the idea
of doing a revert? What's a revert then?
>> So, a revert is simply just I found a
regression. We need to get rid of that
patch out of the tree, but Git doesn't
allow you to change history, so you just
revert the patch. You take the patch
that's in the tree and you apply the
reverse patch, and that's it gone from
that tree. Then you have to make sure
that the revert is also treated just
like any other patch. It goes into the
stable cycle that makes sure it gets
removed from the older stable trees.
Backports should pick up the revert. So,
generally reverts have to have like will
have a tagline for what they're
reverting, so you know exactly this
patch reverses this patch.
>> Okay, that was awesome. So, now we've
covered a lot of the key details and
terms. And if listeners want to know
more, they're welcome to check in the
show notes and we'll provide links to
kernel.org articles and handbooks and
things of that nature. What I wanted to
pick up on next was something that you
mentioned just a moment ago, which were
issues about security concerns. Can you
tell us a little bit about how you do
security reviews or maybe talk a little
bit about how you do performance or
stability reviews in the Linux kernel
maintenance process?
>> I'll deal with security first cuz it's
kind of a special case in some ways. So,
we have a dedicated kernel security
team. I'm not on that team. It's Greg is
probably one of the leaders on that. I
don't know who else is involved. There's
an embargo process, but it's very quick.
I think 7 days is what Linus likes to
give people. Linus is very vocal about
security fixes just being fixes. He
believes there's a lot of theater in
security, so he's very pushy on just
getting fixes into history as quickly as
possible, and that's it's a fix for a
bug. We need to get it upstream and send
it out. But we've built up more like
Greg is building up like a CVE sort of
handling system for the kernel, where
our own CVE handler, but we have a lot
of potential security fixes in the
kernel. And over the last year you may
have seen some news articles and
discussion about that, and like you
know, we're we can never really say a
lot of things for sure if they're a
security problem. Because it's a
security problem in the kernel, it may
not be your security problem in your
kernel, and you need to be in charge of
that. So, if you're a downstream of the
kernel packaging it up in in your
operating system, you probably need to
be more on top of this. That the The
upstream kernel is used in so many
different ways that every specific CVE
that we issue for the kernel may not
apply to your use case. But, the
subtlety in the security industry isn't
quite there yet in that there's a lot of
CV scanners that just take blanket
approaches. There's a lot of, you know,
so security area is definitely a tricky
one. In terms of process, generally
there's a security mailing list. If it's
in your area, you will get CC'd on the
report. You're expected to bring in the
other people in your area who are
responsible. So, you know, I can get the
top-level CC. If it's not something I
directly could fix or know about, I'll
have to bring in people from the people
involved. And, you know, and then we'll
keep it secret for 7 days. If we can't
If we can get a patch out, we'll get a
patch out. But, yeah, generally it
Lately, I think AI-generated reports
have sort of saturating the bandwidth as
well. Some of them are good. Some of
them are bad, but the problem is it's
bandwidth saturation problem. You know,
the bad ones will still cause you to
waste time. In terms of
dealing with other types of regression
like performance issues or things like
that, quite often they just sort of come
up over time. Like, we do try to do In
the last few years, we've moved into CI
a lot more, but one of the biggest
challenges of the Linux development
process is it doesn't really integrate
well with how CI works. And, it's where
I quite like having I also work on some
other projects where we have full GitLab
CI processes where every merge request
goes through a full CI run before being,
you know, merged. I like that. It makes
life so much easier. But, the Linux
kernel is not designed for that because
of our workflow. There's no like central
point to pick these patches up and push
them through a centralized CI system.
And, everyone has built bespoke CI. And,
again, a central CI wouldn't scale.
Like, one of the problems with CI is it
like it needs resourcing and if we had a
central the scaling is going to kill it.
So, having them per subsystem and having
them more bespoke is probably a good
thing. We have a graphics sort of CI
pipeline. It's not quite there yet.
We're working It's been worked on over
the last year. Some of the Qualcomm
being quite pushing on it. The idea is
that I would love to see a pre-merge CI
system that I would know that when a
patch set gets to me it's gone through
some sort of CI, but quite often that's
not true today. A lot of Intel have done
a sort of a CI integration with the
mailing list, which is janky, but it
works as in they get patches on the
mailing list, they apply them to a tree
and they push them through to CI and
they report out through a tool called
patchwork. I know AMD have some internal
CI that they will push their next
kernels through as well and it's kind of
very patchy the coverage in that area,
but often that's how we, you know,
initially we'll find regressions and
things like that are through that, but
then Valve will tell us if this they
updated the new Steam Deck and it's
suddenly slower. You know, things like
that will come through. Also, a lot of
regressions in performance and stuff can
be it can look like it's a graphics
problem, but it's actually a power
management problem because, you know,
they're so tightly integrated now all
the pieces of your your SOCs and your
GPUs is that there's so many pieces to
them. Yeah, you could suddenly have a
clock change and yeah, that can cause
some problems. So, it's CI it's it's
also you have to know the architecture
of the whole system to track those down.
>> Thanks, that's helpful. I wanted to pick
up on two phrases that you used. You
mentioned CI and I know there's
something called kernelci.org
and before that you mentioned B4. Can
you tell our listeners very specifically
like what are the things you run in CI
and then how do tools like B4 help you?
Do you run them in CI or do you run them
on your developer workstations? What's
the process there, Dave?
>> Yeah, there's no good central standard
here at all. So, I'll go B4 is a tool
that is replaces email for getting
patches from you to the mailing lists.
We've
the two kernel tools group, Constantine
is the main guy there. I have developed
a thing called public inbox, which is a
mailing list archiver holster that we
use as kind of a repository of a
database of all of the patches ever kind
of sent to any mailing list. Everything
is in this public inbox sort of
hierarchy. And B4 is a tool then that
lets you submit things
to those inboxes. In reverse, there's a
tool called LEI,
which is for pulling things out and lets
you query those inboxes. So, I use an
example to query for all the pull
requests in the last week, get them into
a local mailbox, and then I process them
locally. So, it's just tooling that
avoids using SMTP as an
email server and lets you go beyond
that. But, in terms of projects like
Kernel CI and we have a GitLab CI
project on freedesktop.
There's not much sort of coherence
there, I suppose. That's why different
subsystems kind of use them in vague
ways. There's a little bit more like
it's generally after-the-fact CI as
well. It's generally stuff goes through
CI after it's been merged to Linux tree,
after it's been put in next. There's
very rarely we have CI in advance of the
patches going into someone's tree. Yeah,
and that's something I'd like to change.
Like I encourage people in my area to
try and develop things that to help me
change that. I probably ain't I'm not
the person to do that, but I definitely
encouraged and open to workflows that
allow that to happen because I see the
value in it. But, yeah, in terms of
overall, like Kernel CI has has the
name, but in terms of whether all of the
kernel goes through it is not really
that doesn't really actually happen. And
again, you know, we also had a a number
of robots over the year. Intel had a a
tool called Zero-Day, which was
something that would apply patches to
it, but sometimes Zero-Day would be You
never knew when Zero-Day was going to
respond to you. Zero-Day could tell you
about your patch a week later, it could
tell you an hour later, it could tell
you a month later. A lot of these again
are after-the-fact things. You send
something to the mailing list and maybe
you get a response. Trying to bring the
window of timing on those and trying to,
you know, constrain those again is hard
because you know, there's so many kernel
patches and scaling is hard. So, the
Intel CI is probably one of the has
lasted quite a while in that they get
patches on the mailing list. I see them
apply. I see them runs. And it just it
works. But, it's very strong together
with your baling twine and stuff. It's
not a very coherent system.
>> Thanks for those clarifying comments
about how you're using tools and how
you're using CI. I did want to follow up
with one final question in this area. Do
you use various types of fuzzing
techniques when it comes to the DRM
subsystem, or is fuzzing used in any
other parts of reviewing patches in the
Linux kernel?
>> Fuzzing seems to go through like like
popularity phases, I suppose. It becomes
popular for a while. They find all the
fuzzing bugs, and then it stops. We
don't have anything specific in our
subsystem for it, but there's a upstream
project called syzkaller. Syzkaller is
notorious for finding the weirdest race
conditions in the weirdest places in
that and then providing you with very
detailed information on how it did that.
It literally intelligently spams all of
the kernel APIs in various orders with
various random things. Like, so it's not
fuzzing in the sense of it's sending
complete garbage to things. It knows the
structure of the ioctl interfaces. It
knows the structure of the system call
interfaces. So, it knows it needs to
pass in valid file descriptors to get
past. Cuz otherwise, 99% of your fuzzing
stops at the first block. So, it's
intelligent enough to try and get down
into the kernel depth. It's a quite a
cool project, but yeah, we don't
specifically use that, but we respond to
reports of that. But again, it comes
down to you can get overwhelmed with
auto-generated reports of syzkaller
problems because some of them are so
deep and so niche that like no user is
ever going to hit these. They can often
get pushed to the background. They can
be that one-in-a-million problem. And
that's good to know, but sometimes we
have to over-prioritize them, and that's
often a bad thing.
>> Okay, that was really helpful.
>> Struggling to advance in the software
industry
as an experienced professional ready to
lead? Pull ahead of your competition
with the new Software Professional
certification from IEEE Computer
Society.
Your expertise certified by the most
trusted professional organization in
computing.
Take the lead in your career. Sign up at
computer.org/certification
today.
>> [music]
>> So, I wanted to talk briefly about how
people get involved with the Linux
kernel maintenance process. I know you
have this idea of new people submitting
a patch or making a suggestion for a
change. How does it work if one of our
listeners finds what they think is a bug
or has an idea for a performance
improvement? Can you give us a few
insights on what that process might look
like?
>> The world has changed over the years. I
think the best way to get involved now
is to get a job where they tell you to
get involved, but secondary to that, if
you have an your personal issues are
generally the best way to start on
something. If it's a problem you have on
your laptop or in your system that
you're seeing, then yeah, you have a
sort of an incentive to want to go down
that road and dig into it. And it's the
code's all there. I encourage people to
go out look into it. Like, use your
ChatGPT or whatever. Use Gemini. Use
those to even interrogate what you think
about the code or trying to figure it
out. Work through
If you find the area of the kernel the
problem is in, well, then find the
community attached to that area. There
is no single Linux kernel community.
There's the Linux kernel mailing list.
That is not the place you start. The
Linux kernel mailing list is where you
drop patches that kind of you aren't
sure what to do with. And very often it
will get ignored. It's more of a It's
not a central place for development. You
have to find your community. So, if you
want to work in the graphics, you go,
"Okay, well, this is a DRM subsystem.
Where are those developers? Are they on
They're on their DRM GitLab or they're
on You know, can I find them on IRC
maybe? Can I find them on Discord? Are
they Is there a community of people I
can actually talk to and say, 'Is this a
good idea?'" You could send a mail mail
to the maintainer. Quite often, you will
likely get a reply. Maintainer dependent
because some of us just get so many
emails that they don't all We don't get
to them all. I try to get to a lot of
the new one new people asking questions
by diverting them to the person who
could better answer that question in in
the area, but not all of it is a steady
thing. But yeah, find a community, find
out how they work, lurk for a while,
like maybe watch their workflows a bit,
maybe read a few patches, maybe get an
like get an idea of how the patches in
that subsystem are reviewed, maybe
review a few patches if you're feeling
that you know enough C and you've
learned enough about the area, you know.
So like you can start by You can always
do a drive-by patch, right? That's where
you just drop the patch and hope someone
applies it and never look at it again.
And that's often for small things,
that's probably fine. But if something
you're actually interested in getting
into kernel development, that's often
the best way to start is find your
personal itch that you want to scratch,
and then work with the community to
figure out how to do that. I do get off
asked a lot "Can you give me a project
to work on or something to start me
off?" And that's a tough question
because without knowing your level of
ability and skill, without having
mentored you on something, I can't
really give you that. We've tried to
construct to-do lists, and they they
work in some ways. We've had some
success with keeping to-do lists
upstream as long as we maintain those
and I give sort of levels of easy versus
hard. But quite often you find like if
an experienced developer hits a
roadblock that is just a simple to-do
list item, they're going to go straight
through it. It'll be a patch 10 minutes
later. So you have to have things that
core developers don't want to fix right
now because otherwise they would just
fix them right now cuz they're
important. So it's like it's hard to
find that balance of tasks and you know,
and we often have new projects that are
up and coming where there's like a the
project has started, like our Nova
project, which you know, is a GPU driver
that's started. It's like people want to
get involved, but it's like it's kind of
at a problem stage where we can't get
people involved because we haven't
opened up the window where it's
parallelizable. Right now it's very
serial. We need to get certain things
done, and we need to get to a baseline,
and we haven't got there yet. So it's
hard to get people to join until that
baseline's achieved unless they know
some of the the deeper parts of it are
are working on it full-time.
>> Thanks, that's really helpful. Now, a
while ago you mentioned the idea of a
patch series as having like a cover
letter. So what goes along with a patch
series beyond the cover letter, how do
you show like what its tags are, how it
was tested, how it was verified, what
fuzzing it went through? Can you give us
a little bit more of a sense of what a
patch series looks like for the Linux
kernel?
>> Honestly, essentially a patch of letter,
none of that generally goes into them,
unfortunately. I think we would like
that to happen more, but often the cover
letter is just often it has like the
list of I said version. So, say you sent
a patch series out once, it's been
reviewed, it's probably hit a few
fuzzers, somebody may have gone through
a CI system. The second time you send it
out, you may include some of that
feedback into the cover letter. You may
say changes since the previous version
are because I got this feedback from a
reviewer, I got this feedback from an AI
reviewer, I got this feedback from a CI
system, the Cisco found a problem. You
know, something like that is often in
there, but it's not essential. It's not
we don't have to put in that it went
through a CI. Often I say the CI is
after the fact, so we reviewed a patch
for more like aesthetic and you know,
functionality, and then when it's
merged, we figure out whether there's
actually a major regression we didn't
spot. And to honest, we get a we we
don't spot them all.
One of the advantages we're seeing with
AI reviewers is that they find some of
these things that we humans just aren't
we might spot them one day and the next
day we might not. And you know, we're
not the consistency isn't always there.
So, yeah, it just goes down to ideally
yeah, we'd have all the information
that's pertinent to the person applying
the series to make it easier for them to
apply your series. But in practice, it
varies between two lines and essays.
>> Okay, that's helpful. I remember before
you mentioned the idea of long-term
support or LTS, and we've already talked
about things like backporting, but we
haven't yet defined the word downstream
kernel. What does downstream mean?
>> So, from the kernel's point of view,
downstream is any kernel that isn't
Linus's, I suppose. And maybe I can pull
it out to being any kernel that isn't
stable. So, Linus and Greg's trees.
Anything that's not theirs and isn't
feeding into them. So, I wouldn't
consider like the DRM tree being a
downstream because we are going to feed
our tree into Linus. But, if you're a
consumer of Linus's tree like Red Hat is
through Rail, through Fedora, or Android
has like you know, a Chrome OS has,
Ubuntu. So, any of those sort of kernels
that are not just taking Linus's kernel
and packaging them up, those are what we
would consider downstream trees. Any
trees that have diverged from the Linux
core and added backports of their own,
drivers of their own, things that
haven't gone upstream of their own. So,
yeah, a bespoke kernel that is for some
use case.
>> Okay, that's really helpful. Now, one of
the other things that I remember you
talking about before is what I might
call a cross-subsystem change. So, like
for example, you mentioned how power
management could influence things that
are related to DRM. And as a long-time
Linux user myself, I have had that
happen. So, can you talk a little bit
about cross-subsystem changes in the
Linux kernel? And how do you manage
that? It seems incredibly complicated.
>> It's one of the more difficult aspects,
I suppose, in some ways to handle
because you often get a bug report in
through you know, through your handling
system and you're then going, "Okay,
well, now is this my problem?" And you
go looking for it and you dig through
the kernel and you decide it's not your
problem, but how do you then tell the
person who submitted that bug report,
"You need to go annoy these other
people." Subsystems will go and bring
that other person other subsystem in and
try and talk to them. Like, we have good
relations between the power management
people and the you know, the GPU people
because we know we need to have those
problems worked out. But, like you know,
we don't If somebody comes in and says,
"My network card suddenly broke my
graphics card." then it's started That's
another level up of how do we figure
that out? Like you know, those sort of
problems. Quite a lot of that though is
often mitigated through the core kernel
as in like you try to use standard
kernel APIs. You don't try to make cross
dependencies between your areas without
having them go through some sort of
standard core kernel piece. And often
the core kernel piece is then maintained
by people on both sides of that sort of
divide. So, we have things like what the
DMA buff subsystem, which is like a way
of sharing memory between devices. We
have that, so graphics people will use
that, but also our DMA people will use
that. And but we will talk through the
DMA buff layer, and when we have issues
or bugs, we resolve them around that
sort of the community around DMA buff
will be a slightly different community
than the community around the core
graphics or the mode setting team. So,
it's a Yeah, we I say with power
management has often got a little
community around it of people who are
both GPU people and power management
people. So, again, it's mostly like a
social aspect of trying to get the
people to actually talk to each other
and trust each other that when they say
they have a problem, they believe each
other.
>> So, can you tell a story or give a
concrete example of like a some type of
cross subsystem change, and then how you
as maintainers actually decided, quote
unquote, whose fault it was and who
actually had to make the fix?
>> Quite often, we don't hit that many at
that level. Quite often, like big
subsystem cross subsystem changes are
well planned out. We will talk about
them for maybe could be a a year, could
be 6 months out. Like, you know, we want
to make a big change to a kernel API.
It's either something that's very
automatic, and I don't ever see it. It
happens completely in someone else's
tree. It goes to Linus, and I All I get
is the fallout when I have to fix the
conflicts and stuff, but that's just
part of the job. At a more core level, a
lot of the time, producing core
functionality in the kernel that is
cross subsystem is where it gets tricky.
Getting that, like taking like DMA buff
into the kernel and then making it
usable for everyone, those discussions
are harder because you often have a very
opposing views on how these things
should work, and some people will take
very strident positions and not want to
move. And how do you Our negotiation on
those topics is actually quite a lot of
my job is impedance mismatching your
engineers who are very focused on how
they think something should work and
engineers who think other things should
work. And it's like, "Yeah, you're both
right, but that doesn't solve the
problem." It's like, "I need you to come
together and work out how it's going to
work between you." And you get
personality issues there. And again,
what part of my job, and I think part of
why I like doing a lot of maintenance
work I do is is is dealing with the
people and just solving those problems
between them. But, that's quite a lot of
it. It's just that social trust aspect
is very important. And again, you find
if you build One of our That's what
That's come up and Simona talks about
this quite often is that when we have
developers build things inside companies
and then upstream them, we often don't
get that commonality. But, it's not even
often about the commonality of the code
as much as it's about having the
community of the people who understand
the problem talking to each other. So,
we've had this problem with I suppose
one of our graphics drivers went a bit
rogue a few years ago and did a whole
lot of development work internally in
the company and then decided they were
going to upstream that work. And when
they started upstreaming that work, we
started seeing major structural problems
with some of the other work they'd been
doing leading to that work. And it was a
the driver had diverged maybe by a year
or two. You know, we're not closely
monitoring. The trust system is there
for a good reason. But, the problem that
came out of that is like they literally
that didn't understand the problems that
other people were solving. And again, we
often have case where someone will go,
"Okay, well, I've got this problem."
"Oh, we tried that 5 years ago and we
couldn't do it." It's like, "Well, where
did you try it?" "Oh, we did it
internally." And it's like, "Well, if
you'd done that in public, we'd have
that evidence that you tried it so the
other person wouldn't waste their time."
So, it's building up that sort of
community infrastructure, especially
with new technologies are coming along
like memory management, things have
changed on GPUs and stuff. And building
up that knowledge base and that core of
people that understand the problem with
that in the industry is that in the each
company there's like one or two of these
people. But, you want all of the
industry experts in the same place to
solve that for Linux. And that's getting
those five or 10 people to talk and
trust each other is the tricky part.
>> Yeah, thank you for saying that. You've
used the word trust several times and
you've talked about how this is as much
a technical issue as it is a human issue
as well. And that makes me think of
perhaps like a bigger picture question.
You know, as you're going through an RC,
I'm guessing you must have some rough
idea of hey, this RC is really healthy.
It's going well. Or oh, this RC is
really struggling. We're going to have
to go to five or six or beyond. Can you
take a big step back and give us a sense
of how you're gauging like the overall
health of a release cycle?
>> Linus is really good at this. I'm not as
good. Linus is This is one thing you'll
see in all of his weekly RC emails. He
will always give us sort of a feeling
health warning of oh, there's a lot more
patches in this than I expect. Like he
does a lot of trend watching. So, he'll
watch the trends in the last like five
10 kernels and he'll have a innate
knowledge of this feels big. This feels
like there's too many patches. Some of
these fixes are big fixes. Like
oh, he'll often look at the trend and
say oh, there's like way too many
patches here. But then he'll look at
sampling of those patches and say oh,
they're all quite small. They're all
quite self-contained. They're fixing one
small bug. It just happens we're fixing
a lot of small bugs. But if he does that
and he sees large changes like you're
modifying multiple things in a subsystem
that aren't reverts. Like we generally
reverts are fine. But something that's
doing a you know, a pretty intricate
change to fix a bug. He will get a bit
antsy and he'll be like, okay, no, I'm
not too comfortable releasing RC7
straight to final. I might I think we
should do an RC8. Quite often security
issues can cause things like that. Like
Spectre Meltdown, things like the big
ones. Those those cause that problem.
For me personally, yeah, I I keep an eye
on sizing as well when I cuz I generate
my weekly request to Linus. I'll keep an
eye on sizing. Generally, I also keep an
eye on the each so every week I
generally get maybe four standard pull
requests. I get our miscellaneous tree.
I get the AMD folks, the Intel and two
trees from different Intel teams. And
those are like my baseline. If those
don't come in by Friday, I'm like
something's gone wrong. But then
there'll always be maybe one other. Like
so maybe MSM will come in with like the
Qualcomm fixes for the for the They
don't do weekly. So, like they might be
two or three weeks I'll get a big bunch
of those. And sometimes those ones are
like, okay, there's a lot of changes in
here. Could he have broken this up or is
there some other things? And that's sort
of like I I go down that gauge that. But
for me, yeah, generally I find by RC4 or
five, things do taper off. We do
generally get a sort of a like a shorter
things drop down to like the whole pull
request being in less than 100 lines or
200 lines. If I start seeing pull
requests where I'm seeing five or 600
lines changed that after RC56 I'm I will
dig in a bit and look into it. But yeah,
it's kind of a instinct built over time
that you just your comfort levels. We
usually find the really big problems
early and it's then comes out to with
graphics there's so many like yeah, if
you break something central it's very
obvious, but laptops are so diverse.
There's so many different ways laptops
can break and panels like it's not even
one laptop it's like every model of a
laptop could have different panel and
the panel yeah, so it's like those
things are always going to be on a bit
more of a long tail, but they're not
showstoppers. Like I generally treat a
regression where somebody has a black
screen as kind of a showstopper because
it's like yeah, having a black screen
means I can't install Linux. Yeah, I
generally try to get those fixed as
quickly as possible or by reverting or
moving up you know, pushing people, but
yeah, it's quite a hard to describe a
showstopper when you're in the area of
like yeah, every mostly works and the
price of kernel as a whole the kernel
even at RC1 mostly works pretty well.
It's very rarely even at RC1 that it's a
complete like what we call a dumpster
fire, but the potential is still there,
but the process is built in a quite well
now that that's a lot rarer than it used
to be. Like it used to be installing RC1
on your laptop was like will I have a
file system tomorrow, you know.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, that's really helpful and I think
it gives us a good intuitive sense of
what we mean by the health of an RC. In
a moment I want to talk a little bit
about how AI is changing your landscape
and I also want to talk briefly about
Rust in the Linux kernel. But before we
move to that phase of our show and then
draw the episode to a conclusion, is
there anything that we haven't covered
that you thought we should cover?
>> No, I think we've gotten sort of the
basic level topics.
>> Okay. And if listeners are curious in
wanting to know more, I'll pass along
some links in the show notes both to
other episodes of Software Engineering
Radio and in many of the resources that
Dave and I have gathered. Now quickly
Dave, I wanted to talk about using AI
because you've mentioned that several
times. You talked about how you could
have a coding agent do a review of part
of the Linux kernel for you, and then
maybe point out a potential regression
or a security concern. Can you tell our
listeners a little bit more about how
you're integrating AI into your
maintenance workflow?
>> Well, over the last sort of year, this
has become a like a topic of both
interest and contention, I suppose, in
the community. But, the way I personally
got involved was at the last maintainer
summit, Linus said like, "Oh, I'm
actually seeing good reviews coming out
of some of the like he he had had access
to some people at Google and some people
at Meta who had been doing some of this
work, and they've been showing him some
of the reviews, and he was like, "I'm
quite impressed." And he says, "One
thing that happens every year at
maintainer summit is we complain about
not having enough reviewer bandwidth,
not having enough reviewers." You know,
it's like it's a common refrain. And
he's like, "If this can help or find
problems, that's a good place. You know,
we we should probably start looking into
this." I was like, "Okay, well, that's a
pretty good that he's he's interested."
I talked to I called Chris Mason at Meta
who's been leading their work on this.
He actually wrote framework for
regression finding for using AI. So, it
was very specifically focused on
prompting the AI to sort of find
regressions. And how he tested it was by
running it on older kernel patches, and
then finding fixes for those older
kernel patches. And if those fixes were
for a regret And if the AI identified
the initial problem in the initial patch
review, then, you know, obviously the
system is useful. And he's found that it
was catching regressions. I I can't
remember what the false positive was,
but it's in the 50%. So, that's
interesting, because if we can avoid
having to put fixes patches in by having
an automated reviewer and give you
feedback, then why wouldn't we? Even if
there's noise in that system, it's still
better like the signal is on 50% is a
pretty good signal noise. Even if it's
not that, finding those regressions is
still a lot of work. It's expensive.
Like, when a regression actually gets
into the Linux kernel and gets out into
the world, that costs like actual money
in the world, even if you're the process
isn't seeing that. And having an AI find
those, yeah, that there should be value
in that. We need to work on it. What I
personally did and this is due to a like
a we also have a lot of AI stuff dealing
with in Red Hat. So, I was like, well, I
I was like, I'll take that mandate I
have from Red Hat and Linus and sort of
put together. So, I wrote a I used
Claude to write a Claude reviewer where
it just passes the patch series to
Claude Opus 4 6 and then gives a good
like patch by patch review. I didn't
concentrate on regressions as much. I
just wanted more of a an overall review
of the series and a patch by patch
review. Gives a basic set of problems
that I haven't enforced this. I haven't
pushed this onto the community. I built
side public inbox infrastructure that
was there on free desktop. So, you could
actually use the same tools to pull this
the patch reviews as you could pull
patches with using the an alternate
server. All the training should still
work. So, it's there as an option right
now. I'm also kind of using it as a
reference. I'm I'm running it manually
at the moment and generating it every
day or two, but it's like if I see
regressions and then I can go back and
look at this reference and say, "Look at
Look, it spotted that problem and now we
have this problem months later." I'll
get that feeling that maybe we should be
pushing on this more. But, even last
week or two Google unveiled I'm going to
say it Shashlik or something I think
it's called a patch review system. So, I
need to catch up on that and maybe get
them to start reviewing the DRM patches
using that system if they're interested
because my one is a bit junky, but it it
was doing the job for me for what I want
to figure out. But, I think the value at
the moment people are definitely seeing
value in AI patch review. Code
generation, I still there's potential
and I don't think I've seen a few
patches generated with the help of
Claude and they haven't been horrible.
So, again, I still I'm quite open to see
where that goes. I definitely think
there will there will be potential for
doing it and will pick up I I would
guess in the next year. I think Opus and
Gemini are starting to get to the level
where you you can actually do some
actually decent stuff with them. So, I
think it will develop heavily in the
next year.
>> I know that we could do an entire
episode just about using AI to do code
review in the Linux kernel and I hope
you'll continue to write blog posts on
this topic because I'm sure our
listeners will be excited to learn more.
Before we end the show, I did want to
talk about one other thing that I
remember reading on your blog, which is
the integration of the Rust programming
language in the Linux kernel. Once more,
I know that we could do a full episode
on this topic, but can you give your our
listeners a little sense of how Rust is
playing a role in the Linux kernel?
>> Yeah, actually my reasoning for using
getting behind the Rust effort is
actually not probably what people would
expect. And I think you could probably
do a really good episode with two people
I know about Rust in the Linux kernel
from a technical standpoint. My push for
getting behind the Rust effort was
actually more social and community
focused. I was at I think it was Linux
Plumbers Conference maybe 2 years, 3
years ago. Can't remember the exact
timelines. So, maintainers summit the
Linux 30 people summit that's co-located
usually with Plumbers Conference and we
have our private meeting at the pub
conference. One of the big complaints in
the private meeting over the years is
we're all getting older. There's you
know, we've got a lot more gray beards.
Like people are in their 50s now that
we're in their 20s when they started
this journey. So, it's definitely the
community's aging. And simultaneously at
people complaining at that conference, I
met some people from the graphics
subsystem. Just starting to talk to
people in the hallway tracks. And one
guy came up to me and said, "Oh, I
really like working in the graphics
subsystem. There's loads of There's a
young group of people working here.
They're all very interesting, excited. I
like going to conference and meeting
them." And I I didn't know this existed
really because I don't work down at the
level, but she said there's this good
community that she likes to be a part
of. And I was like, "Okay, I didn't
create that, but I
we facilitated that in the DRM subsystem
by being open to different things and
not being so strict in our methods of
developing the kernel." But then as
well, the next time I was talking to
some few of the Rust people and I was
like, "These are very young people.
These are again a group of people who
are in their like maybe in their 20s,
some in their 30s." Yeah, but they're
they're a younger cohort of developers
than the people I'm normally used to
dealing with. And I was like, "Look, I
think there is a good way we can bring
these together. I think having young
people coming into the kernel using Rust
as a mechanism is is valuable and having
it that different perspective and having
it different way of doing it. And so I I
was like, well, if I'm getting feedback
that there's young people in the DRM sub
system and it's an interesting area that
to develop that in and there's young
people writing well, I think I should be
supportive of putting Rust in the
kernel. I see it going to happen. I'll
help accelerate it. I'll facilitate it.
And I I I I stood up at the Rust
conference mini conference and said,
"Yeah, I'm open to doing this. Let's do
it." Now, in terms of when I say that of
me doing anything about it I didn't do
anything about it. I just said I was
happy to have people do something about
it. And that's been my So it's my
working model over the years is like
just say you're open to the idea. Don't
You don't have to do it. It's like I'm
willing to make space for this to happen
and and facilitate it. And what I
actually end up doing was going back
inside Red Hat, finding one of my
engineers who was a a working on the
stuff in New Folsom at the time and he
was a really good C developer and
suggesting to them like they don't work
for me. They're in my one of my teams,
but I I'm not a manager. I was like,
"Would you be interested in Rust?" And
they went through the cycle of I don't
really like this. I don't really like
it. And now they really love it. And now
they're one of the Rust core
maintainers. So it's like encouraging,
building that group. Like you know, if
you wanted to talk about the technical
aspects of Rust in the kernel, talk to
someone like Danilo or Miguel would be
ideal because they really know the
details of it. For me, it is just about
bringing in new people into the
community and expanding the Linux kernel
community. And like I see the safety
aspects and I see those aspects of it. I
I I actually see good value in them,
especially we have a graphics sub
system. We have a very wide API to the
user space. It's often exploited. So I
would rather we don't have that. I'd
rather that's a safe API as much as
possible. And same with the hardware
that we keep that safety concerns with
the hardware interfaces as much as
possible. I see Rust accelerating the
ability to deliver GPU drivers. I see it
being much faster that we can build a
lot more common infrastructure. We can
avoid making a lot of the C mistakes
we've repeatedly make. You know, a long
time C developers will say, "We could do
that in C." And I'm like, yes, we can,
but we've repeatedly not. You know,
yeah, review can catch this, but we've
repeatedly failed. It's like, yes, like
these are all the fact that yes, if you
have the best C program in the world on
a bad day, we'll still make that
mistake. Rust gives you a lot more you
can't do that. The compiler stops you.
You can build into your type system the
fact that the compiler will stop you
doing you know, let you do a stupid
things and especially with lifetimes.
Lifetimes are one of the hardest things
to get right in the Linux kernel. The
lifetime we made this like 20 years of
lifetime mistakes that would describe a
lot of the kernel development process.
Like it we have made every lifetime
mistake over the years, you know. In
terms of, you know, from when we moved
from single processor to SMP, but even
moving now to threaded like interrupts
and all these things all these changes
over the years find new ways that we've
messed up our lifetimes. Hot plugging
devices, lifetimes messed up. They've
all involved been designing new things
and you know, getting that right and
embedding that in your type system is
quite valuable to stop making those
mistakes.
>> Yeah, thanks for all of these insights.
It's really been a lot of fun to have
this conversation as we've been focusing
on Linux kernel maintenance and I
recognize there's many technical details
that we didn't really cover, but I'm now
interested in you taking a big step back
as we conclude our episode. So, you've
been working on kernel maintenance for
more than two decades. Can you tell us a
little bit briefly what has stayed the
same and what has changed? Give our
listeners a little bit of a picture as
we conclude the episode.
>> Yeah, it's an interesting question. I
think the essentials of it have stayed
the same. I think the basic you write a
patch, you fix a problem, goes through
the tree. That that that has the core of
it has remained the same. There's like,
yeah, there's a mailing list, there was
people, but the scale of it has so much
changed and the level for yes, you have
a patch to it has gone from like, you
know, yeah, you have a a patch, but now
you should probably a lot more you need
to do more with that patch to get it to
a quality standard that's acceptable for
the kernel. I think the quality of the
kernel has changed substantially in that
20 years. The quality of our process for
producing it has solidified into an
actual process as opposed to what it was
10 20 years ago where it was just like
randomly just you know, there was no
timelines, there was no process. It was
very shoot from the hip, I suppose. So,
now it's like yeah, it's very
formalized, it's very structured. I
would say it's like going to be less
fun, but less fun is important in that
like yeah, you can't make suddenly wide
raging memory management changes that
destabilizes half the world's computers.
That's probably not a good thing to be
doing anymore. So, yeah, it's like you
know, you definitely have it's matured a
lot, but I still think the core aspect
of hacking on hardware devices and stuff
is still at least for me very appealing.
Like I still yesterday I was writing
code for Nvidia GPU drivers even though
it's you know, it's just stuff to do and
it's like I still like having a hardware
device. I just got an Nvidia Spark box
and I just getting that lit up with open
source Linux drivers is like something
that still appeals to me even 20 years
later like that whole aspect of it.
>> So, thank you very much for your
enthusiasm. It's really contagious. And
if I could say on a personal note, for
someone who's been using Linux for
decades myself, thank you for all of the
work you and your many colleagues have
done because for me using Linux has been
a genuine source of joy in the same way
that this has been a joy-filled and
awesome conversation. Dave, is there
anything that we haven't covered that
you think we should conclude on?
>> No, I think just people if you're
interested in the Linux kernel, just get
out there and find a niche, scratch it,
submit some patches, you know, the
community's out there. We're we're
always happy to have new people join it.
>> Okay. Thanks for all these insights,
Dave. This is Gregory CapHamer signing
off for Software Engineering Radio.
>> [music]
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter,
>> [music]
>> or through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
>> [music]
>> This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.